New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Records 1991.0009
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
- Record Group 3: Annual Reports, 1835-1976
  The Annual Reports Record Group contains reports from the Accounting Department to the Interstate Commerce Commission, state regulatory agencies, and public utility commissions, as well as stockholder reports from the Secretary's Department. The annual reports to the ICC and state agencies were the overall responsibility of the Comptroller, who was in charge of the Accounting Department. The intrinsic importance of the records, however, warranted their separate treatment from the Accounting and Secretary departments' records.
  This record group contains annual reports to the stockholders, to the ICC, and to state regulatory agencies, as well as working papers and appraisal reports. The stockholders annual reports were compiled by the Board of Directors for the stockholders, usually in conjunction with the company's annual meeting. Annual reports filed with the public utility commissions in Connecticut, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, and New York contain information very similar to that submitted to the ICC; in cases where the carrier was not an interstate operator, these state reports are the only reports available.
  The detailed description lists the contents for all of the boxes in Record Group 3, Series 1-6.
  - Series I: Annual Reports to the Stockholders, 1835-1972
    This series is divided into two subseries: New Haven Railroad, 1873-1972, and Subsidiary Companies, 1835-1968. The series contains annual reports to the stockholders, state legislatures, or to courts during periods of trusteeship. The reports contain financial and operating statistics of a more general nature than that of the ICC reports (Series II). The purpose of the reports was to inform stockholders of the financial status and well-being of the company. The reports list the Board members and officers as well as provide information on income and expenses, investments, and operating statistics. In addition, the reports contain a brief narrative summary of the company's activities for the year in question. Reports issued by the NHRR will sometimes contain information on subsidiary operations. Some annual reports contain maps, while later versions include photographs. The reports are printed, bound volumes in most cases; some of them, however, are handwritten or are photocopies. The ANNUAL REPORTS TO THE STOCKHOLDERS are organized by railroad, with the NHRR preceding the subsidiaries. The subsidiaries are arranged alphabetically by company name. Within each company, the reports are arranged chronologically.
  - Series II: Annual Reports to the Interstate Commerce Commission, 1888-1968
    This series is divided into two subseries: New Haven Railroad and Subsidiary Companies. The series is composed of reports filed by the NHRR and its subsidiaries in compliance with ICC regulations. The reports contain essential financial, statistical, and operating information of a detailed nature. Included are expenses and income, investments, mileage data, fuel consumption, passenger statistics, employee information, and accidents. One box of reports from the ICC appears at the end of the series. These include reports on NHRR financial transactions, rate investigations and ICC finance docket 21989, Pennsylvannia Railroad and New York Central Railroad merger. The reports are bound, printed volumes. The New Haven Railroad, 1888-1968, is arranged in chronological order. The Subsidiary Companies, 1888-1966, is alphabetically arranged by company name, then in chronological order; gaps within the span dates are not indicated.
  - Series III: Annual Reports to the States, 1874-1957
    This series contains reports filed by the NHRR and its subsidiary companies with various state regulatory agencies as required by law. These states include Connecticut, Massachusetts, New York, and Rhode Island. The reports contain financial, statistical, and operating information pertaining to intrastate commerce in the state to which the report was submitted. The reports are bound, printed volumes. The New Haven Railroad, 1888-1914, reports are in chronological order. The Subsidiary Companies, 1874-1957, reports are arranged alphabetically by company name and then filed in chronological order; gaps within the span dates are not indicated.
  - Series IV: Annual Reports to the Interstate Commerce Commission: Foreign Roads, 1948-1963
    This series contains reports to the ICC and to stockholders from "foreign roads." "Foreign roads" are defined as any operation (railroad) not directly affiliated with the NHRR. Although the exact reason why the records were maintained is unclear, it is likely they were used as a reference source on railroads that did per diem (rental fee for use of tracks) business with the NHRR. The reports are printed, bound volumes. Reports are arranged in a rough chronological order, with each box in alphabetical order by company. Gaps within the span dates are not indicated.
  - Series V: Annual Reports: Working Records, 1931-1959
    This series contains the supporting files related to the preparation of the annual reports required by the ICC, various state regulatory agencies, and stockholder reports. The records include corrections submitted, amendments, requisitions, correspondence, and filing fees. Included are records of both the NHRR and its subsidiaries. The files contain information pertinent to both the annual and quarterly reports to the ICC. The WORKING RECORDS are arranged alphabetically by company name, but preceded by NHRR records. Within each company, the records are in reverse chronological order.
  - Series VI: Appraisal Reports, 1909-1976
    This series contains a small number of appraisal and valuation reports made of the land and physical property directly owned by the NHRR or the land and physical property of NHRR subsidiary companies. Most of these reports were issued by the accounting firm of Price Waterhouse. Information in the valuation and appraisal reports includes right-of-ways, rails, structures and land. NHRR reports are listed first, followed by an alphabetical list of subsidiary company reports. The dates of the actual appraisal and of the report are listed.
- Record Group 4: Comptroller's Records, 1905-1969
  The Comptroller was an elected officer of the New Haven Railroad in charge of the Accounting Department. The Comptroller's Department supervised and directed all accounts relating to receipts and disbursements. The Comptroller had custody of the general books and accounts, vouchers, drafts, payrolls, invoices, interest coupons, bonds, and other evidence of payment; he also maintained the bonds, interest coupons and other evidence of cancelled debt. The office was responsible for preparing annual reports, which evaluated the financial situation of the company, and submitting the reports to the Interstate Commerce Commission (ICC), various state utility regulatory agencies and the stockholders. For ease of access, the ACCOUNTING DEPARTMENT records and ANNUAL REPORTS are maintained as distinct record groups.
  The records of the COMPTROLLER provide the researcher with a better look at company administration and policy-making than the related ACCOUNTING DEPARTMENT records. Few of these records contain routine finance and operation details.
  This record group is divided into three series: I COMPTROLLER II DEPUTY COMPTROLLER III ASSISTANT COMPTROLLER
  Each series is arranged numerically by a number assigned by the company; no topical index to the numbers was found in the records. The box lists that follow are sample topics included in the files rather than a list of each folder in the box.
  - Series I: Comptroller, Bulk, 1944-1964; 1905-1968
    This series documents the activities of the Comptroller. The series shows employee relations in some detail. There are files on employee agreements, payroll and benefits, working conditions and strikes. The series also contains extensive information on passenger fares and relations, including claims. Located here are financial statistics, revenue forecasts, revenue reports, costs studies and audit reports. Apparently, the Comptroller acted as one of the major information distributors in the New Haven Railroad. Information was sent to publications and associations, such as the Association of American Railroads (AAR). The department maintained files on meetings, membership associations, and charities. There is also a substantial amount of information on government relations and tax issues.
  - Series II: Deputy Comptroller, Bulk, 1953-1967; 1915-1969
    This series contains the records of this office which acted as a direct assistant to the Comptroller; most of the files in this series are associated with Deputy Comptroller A. J. Beauton. The DEPUTY COMPTROLLER files do not differ greatly from those of the Comptroller; they include information on subsidiary companies, audits, insurance, expenditures, and agreements. The records in Series I more completely document employee relations and passenger service and relations than does Series II. This series has been combined with Series I for the web presentation of the finding aid.
  - Series III: Assistant Comptroller, Bulk, 1945-1955; 1921-1965
    This series overlaps in content with Series I and II. More than the previous two series, this series contains records similar to those found in the ACCOUNTING DEPARTMENT record group. This series also includes an important subseries of Abandonment Files, which document the last years of operation of branches. These are arranged by rail line within each state. There is also a significant amount of material on the subsidiary companies, including the New York Connecting Railroad, the Connecticut Company and New England Transportation Company. Information on hotel properties, the Grand Central Terminal building, and freight operations is available in this series.
- Record Group 5: Accounting Department, 1890-1970
  The Accounting Department served three basic functions:
  l. to receive revenues for rail services 2. to ensure proper payment of bills and salaries 3. to maintain a record of financial and operating statistics for use in annual reports.
  Company by-laws (l953) state that "the Comptroller shall have general charge of the Accounting Department.... He shall prepare and submit an annual statement of the financial condition of the company.. ." The Accounting office answered to the Comptroller and was responsible for preparing balance sheets and income statements for the NHRR as well as furnishing federal and state regulatory agencies with monthly, quarterly and annual reports. For ease of access, the ACCOUNTING DEPARTMENT, ANNUAL REPORTS, and COMPTROLLERS RECORDS are maintained as distinct record groups.
  The Accounting Department was responsible for contract payments, such as equipment installments, obligations, bond interest and dividends. It collected mortgage installments and interest receivable. The budget was assembled by the Accounting Office. It controlled accounting activities at Grand Central Terminal and oversaw company operation in the terminal area. In addition to its financial responsibilities, the Accounting Department compiled extensive files of railroad operating statistics, such as hourly wage rates, operating cost per train mile/car mile/ton and passenger mile.
  The Accounting Office records are far from complete. They are best used in conjunction with the SECRETARY RECORDS (RG 1), the COMPTROLLERS RECORDS (RG 4), and the BOUND VOLUMES (RG 7) for a more complete picture.
  Many of the records of the Accounting Department were judged to have low informational and research value. Journal entries and vouchers were sampled and heavily weeded, as described below. In addition, the following files were discarded: Grand Central Terminal bills collectable,13 linear feet; Per Diem files, 6 linear feet; and baggage claims, 1 linear foot.
  The detailed description lists the contents for all of the boxes in Record Group 5, Series 1-10.
  - Series I: General Subject Files, Bulk, 1940-1960; 1895-1968
    This series contains a wealth of information on subjects ranging from the history of the Connecticut Company to board meeting data. This catch-all series includes press releases, operating statistics and some Interstate Commerce Committee and Securities and Exchange Commission investigation files. The accompanying container list is not a complete folder listing and researchers are advised to use it only as a general guide to the 36 boxes. The series is arranged in a random fashion by subject heading, and includes material on both the New Haven Railroad and subsidiary companies.
  - Series II: Closed Subject Files, 1920-1970
    This series contains inactive files on matters that were closed. Like the GENERAL SUBJECT FILES above, the series is a mix of completed contracts and agreements as well as noncurrent subsidiary, Interstate Commerce Commission and investment files. Here also are some Abandonments hearings files, l962-69, before the ICC.
  - Series III: Securities and Exchange Commission, 1910-1950
    This series contains reports to the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) filed by the New Haven Railroad and many of its subsidiary lines. These reports, filed in accordance with the Securities and Exchange Act of l934, give information on securities registered by corporations, companies in bankruptcy and receivership, and those that did not file reports with the Interstate Commerce Commission. The series includes the proofs and working papers for the SEC reports, as well as reports on gross earnings and taxes to New York State.
  - Series IV: Portfolios, Bulk, 1933-1948; 1904-1952
    This series contains bound portfolios listing the stocks and bonds owned by the New Haven Railroad and its subsidiary lines. In addition to lists of stocks and bonds, the volumes also contain general statements of income, expenditures, and accounts. Some of the information for the NHRR is presented in an alternate accounting system. The series is arranged in chronological order by year with the NHRR portfolios preceeding the subsidiary lines.
  - Series V: Rate Structure Studies and Cases, Bulk, 1950-1953; 1936-1953
    This series provides the researcher with material which documents, in part, the relationship between the Interstate Commerce Commission and the New Haven Railroad. This series includes reports, testimony transcripts, and printed reports resulting from hearings held by the ICC concerning rate increases. Most of the material presented is financial and statistical data in support of the New Haven's argument. There is also a record of the testimony by those rail users who opposed the rate increase. The records are arranged by case number, then chronologically.
  - Series VI: First Reorganization, 1937-1945
    This series documents, during Interstate Commerce Commission hearings, the impact of the first court ordered reorganization on the New Haven Railroad and its subsidiary lines. These essential accounting records contain a wealth of financial and statistical information within the various reporter's and stenographer's minutes, exhibits, and reports filed with the ICC. The material is arranged either by exhibit number or in a very rough chronological order. First Reorganization records are also located in the SECRETARY RECORDS. Information on the Second Reorganization is located in the TRUSTEES RECORDS.
  - Series VII: Subsidiary Companies, 1938-1962
    This series is composed of records pertaining to a number of New Haven Railroad subsidiaries companies. The Connecticut Company, l948-62, consists of financial statements and reports, contracts, and audit reports. The New England Transportation records deal with Interstate Commerce Commission investigations and quarterly reports, l938-1967. Trial balances, company history, income accounts, and journal entries, l928-196l, are available for the Providence Produce Warehouse. The records from County Transportation pertain to hearings before the New York Public Service Commission; the hearings dockets and minutes cover the period l946-48. Correspondence regarding the sale of the Soundview Transportation Company, l946-48, is contained in this series. Also see Series IX, SUBSIDIARY COMPANIES, in the SECRETARY RECORDS (RG 1).
  - Series VIII: Claims, 1930-1940
    This series deals with death, injury, tax, and property damage claims filed by individuals and corporations with the Federal District Court during reorganization proceedings. These claims were submitted as proof that the New Haven Railroad was in debt to the party involved before it declared bankruptcy. They are arranged in numerical order by file number. An index, including a summary of each claim, is available in the first box of this series. See also the LEGAL DEPARTMENT CLAIMS record group.
  - Series IX: Budget, 1946-1957
    This series contains the working papers, income accounts, estimates, and forecasts used to prepare the company's budget. This series contains the working papers for the budget. The final operating figures are not in this series.
  - Series X: Journal Entries and Vouchers, 1890-1967
    This series contains a sample of journal entries and vouchers for different periods of time for both the New Haven Railroad and its subsidiary lines. The series also contains microfilmed journal entries, 1920-1940. The information contained in the journal entries and vouchers is available in summary form in the BOUND VOLUMES (RG 7). Within the record type, the materials are arranged by company, then chronologically.
    The journal entries and vouchers were sampled to provide a physical example of these record types. Sampling reduced the journal entries from 154 linear feet to one linear foot, and reduced the vouchers from 90 linear feet to one linear foot. The sampling procedure used for the journal entries was to retain one inch of these folded documents from each of approximately 30 randomly-selected boxes, including at least one box from each company represented in the files. A similar procedure was used in sampling the vouchers. Neither sample is statistically reliable.
- Record Group 6: Legal Department Claims, 1915-1975
  The Claims Department reported to the General Attorney's office in the Legal Department. Headed by the General Claim Agent, the Claims Department was divided along state lines with district offices in New Haven, Boston, New York City, and Providence. (This record group contains no claims from the Providence district office.)
  The Claims Department was responsible for investigating personal injury and accident claims of passengers and employees, as well as property damage and fire claims. District claims agents, with the assistance of special representatives, were responsible for investigating the claims and for obtaining all relevant information, including claimant interviews, photographs, medical records, etc. Most claims were settled out of court, but in some cases the claims were eventually brought to civil court, either on the federal or state level. This record group contains files from both out of court settlements and actual court cases. These claims have been sampled from a much larger group of records. The various sampling procedures for each series of claims are explained in the series descriptions below. Photographs have been removed from the discarded records and are located in the New Haven Railroad Photographs Collection. Note that additional claims are located in Series VIII of the ACCOUNTING DEPARTMENT record group.
  The detailed description lists the contents for all of the boxes in Record Group 6, Series 1-3.
  - Series I: Personal Injury Accident Out-of-Court Settlements, 1944-1970
    This series contains completed claim report forms, correspondence, newspaper clippings and photographs. The series is further divided into three subseries: New Haven District, 1944-70, Boston District, 1964-68, and New England Transportation Company, 1944-60. Within each series, the files are arranged numerically by claim file number; the file numbers listed are not inclusive numbers due to the sampling procedures applied to the records.
    New Haven District subseries originally included over 400 linear feet of files. After appraisal it was decided to retain only a 5% representative sample. The first and last box and every 22nd box in between were retained, representing the types of claims files maintained by the company during this 26-year period. The sample is not statistically reliable. The Boston District files originally consisted of 67 linear feet of records, in 27 transfile boxes; one inch of files was retained from each box. New England Transportation Company claim records originally included 20 linear feet and were sampled as follows: 3 inches of files were taken from the first and last boxes and from every 5th box in between.
  - Series II: Personal Injury Accident Court Cases, 1960-1975
    This series contains records of cases heard in Federal District Court, State Supreme Court and Superior Court. The records include completed claims forms, correspondence, hearing transcripts, newspaper clippings and photographs. Series II is divided into three subseries: Connecticut Court Cases, 1960-75, Boston Court Cases, 1960-75, and New York Court Cases, 1960-75.
    Series II was sampled using a "fat file" sampling method in which files one inch thick or more were retained. The New York Court Cases originally contained nine linear feet and was reduced to six linear feet. The Connecticut Court Cases originally contained 14 linear feet and was reduced to six linear feet. The Boston Court Cases contained 50 linear feet and was reduced to 21 linear feet.
  - Series III: Fire and Livestock Claims, 1915-1945
    This series contains claims for damages from fires and to livestock caused by locomotives. All the claims in this series were settled out of court. The record types in this series include completed claims forms, correspondence, and photographs. This subseries was retained intact, with no sampling.
- Record Group 7: Bound Volumes, 1802-1980
  This record group consists of bound volumes which require special shelving because of their format, size, and bulk. In general, the volumes are in poor or fragile condition and should be handled with care. These records were originally created by offices represented in other record groups, or by other companies. The BOUND VOLUMES include records of both the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and its subsidiary and predecessor companies. The subsidiary and predecessor companies are primarily New England transportation companies: railroads, railways, coach lines, and steamship lines; there are also a few companies of other types, such as real estate and coal companies.
  The type of information found within the bound volumes varies widely with each company and may include one or more of the following: organizational, incorporation and termination information; minutes of board of directors' and stockholders' meetings; reorganization proceedings and related trusteeships; acquisitions of other companies; daily financial transactions arranged by date (journal entries) and by account (ledger entries); cash transactions (cash books); balance sheets; annual reports to the Interstate Commerce Commission; stock certificates, registers, journals, ledgers and dividends; bonds and mortgages; and letter books. This record group contains approximately 850 linear feet of material.
  - Series I: New Haven Railroad, 1872-1980